Bernard L. Austin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Bernard L. Austin Papers 1916-1979 (bulk 1937-1968)
MSS61725
Austin, Bernard L. (Bernard Lige), 1902-1979
7,500 items 24 containers plus 3 classified 9.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer and educator. Correspondence, speeches and writings, and subject files documenting Austin's naval career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Anderson, George Whelan, 1906-1992--Correspondence.; Austin, Bernard L. (Bernard Lige), 1902-1979.; Baldwin, Hanson Weightman, 1903-1991--Correspondence.; Bates, Richard W., 1892-1973--Correspondence.; Beakley, Wallace M.--Correspondence.; Burke, Arleigh A., 1901- --Correspondence.; Colbert, Richard G., -1973--Correspondence.; Conolly, Richard L. (Richard Lansing), 1892-1962--Correspondence.; Dennison, Robert L. (Robert Lee), 1901-1980--Correspondence.; Dietrich, Neil K.--Correspondence.; Eccles, Henry Effingham, 1898- --Correspondence.; Edison, Charles A., 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Eller, Ernest McNeill, 1903- --Correspondence.; Gallery, Philip D. (Philip Daly), 1907-1973--Correspondence.; Ghormley, Robert Lee, 1883-1958.; Harrigan, Anthony--Correspondence.; Hayward, John Tucker, 1910- --Correspondence.; Hoyt, Edwin Palmer--Correspondence.; Knoll, Denys W.--Correspondence.; Lovette, Leland Pearson, 1897- --Correspondence.; McManes, K. M.--Correspondence.; Melson, Charles L.--Correspondence.; Moorer, Thomas H., 1912- --Correspondence.; Nimitz, Chester W. (Chester William), 1885-1966--Correspondence.; Orem, Howard E.--Correspondence.; Peniston, Robert C.--Correspondence.; Ramsey, Paul H. (Paul Hubert), 1905-1982--Correspondence.; Smedburg, W. R.--Correspondence.; Stark, Harold R. (Harold Raynsford), 1880-1972--Correspondence.; Vosseller, A. B.--Correspondence.; Watson, Frank T.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Inter-American Defense Board.; Naval War College (U.S.); United States. Navy Department.; United States. Navy --Foreign service--Great Britain.; United States. Navy --History--20th century.; United States. Navy. Fleet, 2nd.; United States. Office of the Chief of Naval Operations.; United States. Office of the Chief of Naval Operations. International Affairs Division.
Subjects
Destroyers (Warships)--United States.; Journalism, Military--United States.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Naval operations.; Military readiness.; Submarines (Ships)--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, British.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Bernard L. Austin, naval officer and educator, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1984, and converted to a gift in 1998.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Bernard L. Austin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified materials.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1902, Dec. 15 Born, Wagener, S.C.
1918-1920 Attended The Citadel, Charleston, S.C.
1924 Graduated, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1924-1926 Served aboard New York (battleship)
1925 Married Isabella Murray Leith
1927-1931 Served aboard submarines R-10 and R-6
1931-1934 Taught physics and chemistry, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1934-1937 Commanded R-11 (submarine)
1937-1941 Press relations officer, Navy Department; special naval observer, Ghormley mission to Great Britain
1942 Commanded Woolsey (destroyer) in Atlantic and Mediterranean waters; assisted in the sinking of German submarine off Casablanca, Morocco
1943 Commanded Foote (destroyer), Destroyer Division 46, and Destroyer Squadron Fourteen in South Pacific; participated in battles off Bougainville, British Solomon Islands
1944-1945 Assistant chief of staff for administration to Chester Nimitz, commander in chief Pacific (CINCPAC)
1946-1947 Attended United States National War College, Washington, D.C.
1949 Attended Imperial Defense College, London, England
1950 Commanded Service Squadron Three in Korean waters
1951-1954 Assistant director and director, International Affairs Division, Office of the Chief of Naval Operations
1954-1955 Commanded Cruiser Division Two
1956-1958 Director, joint staff of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
1958-1959 Commanded Second Fleet
1959-1960 Deputy chief of naval operations for plans and policy
1960-1964 President, Naval War College, Newport, R.I.
1963 President, court of inquiry investigating the loss of the Thresher (submarine)
1964-1967 Chairman, Inter-American Defense Board
1968 President, court of inquiry investigating loss of the Scorpion (submarine)
1979, Aug. 21 Died, Bethesda, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Bernard Lige Austin (1902-1979), a naval officer who achieved distinction as a commander of submarines and destroyers and as an administrator, educator, military diplomat, and press officer, span the years 1916-1979, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1937-1968. The collection is organized into series of Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Classified, Top Secret, and North American Treaty Organization. Austin attended The Citadel at Charleston in his native South Carolina before matriculating at the United States Naval Academy, from which he was graduated in 1924. His first independent command was as captain of the submarine R-11 during 1934-1937. In the late 1930s, while serving as a press officer for the Navy Department, Austin wrote articles on submarine warfare for the Encyclopedia Britannica and the World Book Encyclopedia. His submarine expertise was again called on late in his career when he presided over courts of inquiry investigating the loss of the nuclear powered submarines Thresher (1963) and Scorpion (1968).
Despite his many years in submarines, Austin's principal achievements came during his command of destroyers. His submarine experience proved useful in his first destroyer command, the Woolsey, in 1942 when he participated in the sinking of a German U-boat off Casablanca during Operation Torch, the Allied invasion of North Africa. In 1943, Austin commissioned the destroyer Foote and sailed it to the South Pacific, where he assumed the command of Destroyer Division Forty-Six, which with Destroyer Division Forty-Five comprised Destroyer Squadron Twenty-Three, Arleigh Burke's famed "Little Beavers", the only World War II destroyer squadron to be awarded a presidential citation.
In November 1943, Austin participated in two battles off the coast of Bougainville, British Solomon Islands, which resulted in the sinking of at least nine Japanese warships. He was awarded the Navy Cross and promoted to commodore, making him the youngest flag officer in the Navy at that time. His postwar commands included the supply ships of Service Squadron Three in Korean waters during 1950 and Cruiser Division Two (1954-1955) and the Second Fleet (1958-1959) in the Atlantic. Most of Austin's sea duty is well documented in the correspondence series. Included in the Subject File is a substantial amount of material on his World War II destroyer commands, "R" class submarines, submarine warfare in the early part of World War II, and the Thresher and Scorpion inquiries.
During 1944-1945, Austin served as assistant chief of staff for administration to Chester Nimitz, commander in chief of Allied naval forces in the Pacific (CINCPAC). Other administrative postings included stints on the State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee (1945-1946) and the staff of the National Security Council (1947-1948). During 1956-1958 he was director of the joint staff of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and during 1959-1960 he served as deputy chief of naval operations for plans and policy. All of these administrative and policy billets are well represented in the correspondence, and there are subject files on the National Security Council, State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee, and the reorganization of the armed services after World War II.
From 1960 to his retirement as vice admiral in 1964, Austin served as president of the Naval War College in Newport, R.I., where he emphasized the coordination of curricula among armed forces graduate institutions. Approximately one-fourth of the correspondence results from Austin's years as president of the Naval War College, and several folders on the college, such as minutes of the academic board, are included in the Subject File.
Austin's first foray into military diplomacy was as a member of the Ghormley mission to Great Britain 1940-1941. The task of Admiral Robert Lee Ghormley, "special naval observer," was to negotiate the policy and technical details of naval cooperation between the United States and Great Britain in the event of United States entry into World War II. Austin, as Ghormley's deputy, was the only mission member other than the admiral to participate in all of the meetings with the British political and naval leadership, which included Winston Churchill and Admiral Sidney Bailey. Other postings involving foreign relations were as assistant director and eventually director of the Navy's International Affairs Division (1951-1954) and as chairman of the Inter-American Defense Board (1964-1967). Correspondence from the 1940-1941 period includes letters from Robert Ghormley. Austin corresponded with many South American naval officers during his service on the Inter-American Defense Board and maintained substantial contact through the 1970s with the Brazilian admiral Levy A. Reis. Subject files also includes material on the Ghormley mission and United States-British naval relations during the World War II period.
Austin felt that his role as Navy Department press relations officer during the period 1937-1940 was a major factor in his achieving flag rank. As a press officer, he developed his interest in oral communication into a professional skill. Some of the speeches in the Speeches and Writings File were ghostwritten by him for key naval civilian officials and admirals, such as secretary of the navy Charles Edison and chief of naval operations Harold R. Stark. Austin's correspondents during the period 1937-1940 included Hanson Baldwin, military correspondent of the New York Times.
The Subject File contains detailed material on Austin, including biographical sketches, orders, and personnel records.
Prominent correspondents not previously cited include George Whelan Anderson, Richard W. Bates, Wallace M. Beakley, Arleigh A. Burke, Richard G. Colbert, Richard L. Conolly, Robert L. Dennison, Neil K. Dietrich, Henry Effingham Eccles, Ernest McNeill Eller, Philip D. Gallery, Anthony Harrigan, John Tucker Hayward, Edwin Palmer Hoyt, Dennys W. Knoll, Leland Pearson Lovette, K. M. McManes, Charles L. Melson, Thomas H. Moorer, Chester W. Nimitz, Howard E. Orem, Robert C. Peniston, Paul H. Ramsey, W. R. Smedburg III, A. B. Vosseller, and Frank T. Watson.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Correspondence, 1924-1979
Speeches and Writings, 1924-1967
Subject File, 1916-1974
Classified, 1955-1967
Top Secret, 1955
North American Treaty Organization, 1955-1959
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm84061725
Container List
- Correspondence, 1924-1979 (Box 1-11)
  Letters sent and received with attached related matter.
  Organized into family and general correspondence and chronologically therein.
  - Family, 1936-1979, undated (Box 1)
  - General (Box 1)
    - 1924, Sept.-1943, Dec., (5 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1944, Jan.-1951, Aug., (6 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1951, Sept.-1954, Dec., (7 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1955, Jan.-1958, Mar. See also Classified, Top Secret, and North Atlantic Treaty Organization, (6 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1958, Apr.-1959, Aug. See also Classified and North Atlantic Treaty Organization, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1959, Sept.-1961, July, (6 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1961, Aug.-1962, Aug., (7 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1962, Sept.-1963, Dec., (6 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1964, Jan.-Oct., (5 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1964, Nov.-1967, May See also Classified, (7 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1967, June-1979, Aug., undated See also Classified, (7 folders) (Box 11)
- Speeches and Writings, 1924-1967 (Box 12-16)
  Speeches, statements, articles, article outlines, and poems by Austin and others.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Speeches (Box 12)
    - By Austin (Box 12)
      - 1924-1961, (6 folders) (Box 12)
      - 1962-1963, (7 folders) (Box 13)
      - 1963-1967, undated See also Classified, (6 folders) (Box 14)
      - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - By others (Box 15)
      - 1930-1950, (4 folders) (Box 15)
      - 1952-1964, undated, (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Ghostwritten by Austin, 1939-1948, undated (Box 16)
  - Writings (Box 16)
    - By Austin, 1924-1953, undated (Box 16)
    - By others (Box 16)
      - Poems, 1955, undated (Box 16)
      - Prose, 1931-1940, undated (Box 16)
- Subject File, 1916-1974 (Box 17-24)
  Correspondence, awards, citations, newspaper clippings, drawings, cartoons, ship logs, maps, nautical charts, battle reports, press releases, notes, research material, orders, biographical sketches, resumes, personnel records, chronologies, administrative histories, minutes of meetings, records related to courts of inquiry, lectures, and transcripts of telephone conversations.
  Organized alphabetically by topic or type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Aircraft carriers (Box 17)
    - Constellation fire, 1961 (Box 17)
    - Forrestal christening, 1954 (Box 17)
  - Awards, certificates, and citations, 1942-1964, undated (Box 17)
  - Biographical material, 1946-1960, undated (Box 17)
  - Burke, Arleigh, 1955, 1961, undated (Box 17)
  - Cartoons and drawings, undated (Box 17)
  - Charts and maps, 1916-1946, undated (Box 17)
  - Cruiser Division Two, 1951-1955, undated (Box 17)
  - Destroyers (Box 17)
    - Battles and operations, 1943-1963, undated (Box 17)
    - Converse, 1945 (Box 17)
    - Destroyer Division Forty-Six, 1943 (Box 17)
    - Destroyer Squadron Fourteen, 1944 (Box 18)
    - Foote, 1943-1945, undated (Box 18)
    - Woolsey, 1942, undated (Box 18)
  - Imperial Defense College, London, England, 1948-1949 (Box 18)
  - Inter-American Defense Board, 1964-1967, undated (Box 18)
  - International Affairs Division, United States Navy (OP-35), 1952-1953, undated (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-1959, undated, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - National Security Council, 1951-1953, undated (Box 18)
  - National War College, Washington, D.C., 1949, undated (Box 18)
  - Naval War College, Newport, R.I. (Box 18)
    - Academic Board Meetings, 1960-1964 (Box 18)
    - Global strategy discussions, 1959 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous, 1961-1963, undated (Box 19)
    - Lectures, 1952-1963 (Box 19)
    - Second Conference of the War Colleges of the Americas, 1963 (Box 19)
    - Reference cards, 1960-1963, undated, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 19, Box 20)
  - Navy News, Guam edition, Orders and personnel records, 1924-54 (5 folders) 1945 (Box 20)
  - Orders and personnel records (Box 20)
    - 1924-1954, (5 folders) (Box 20)
    - 1955-1968, undated, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - Press Relations Department, Navy Department, 1939, 1974, undated (Box 21)
  - Press releases (Box 21)
    - 1939-1946, (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - 1957-1960, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Reorganization of armed services, 1944-1960, undated (Box 22)
  - Service Squadron Three, 1951-1953, undated (Box 22)
  - State-War-Navy Coordinating Committee, 1945, undated (Box 22)
  - Submarines (Box 22)
    - Encyclopedia articles by Austin, 1938-1940, undated (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous, 1927-1940, undated (Box 22)
    - "R" class submarines, 1930-1937, undated (Box 22)
    - Scorpion (Box 22)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1969, undated (Box 22)
      - Miscellaneous, 1968, undated (Box 23)
    - Squalus, 1939, undated (Box 23)
    - Thresher (Box 23)
      - Correspondence (Box 23)
        - Miscellaneous, 1963, (4 folders) (Box 23)
        - Official, 1963 (Box 23)
      - Summary of events, 1963 See also Classified (Box 23)
      - Telephone conversations, 1963 (Box 23)
  - Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe (SHAPE),. 1955-1956, undated (Box 23)
  - United States-British naval relations (Box 23)
    - Administrative History of U.S. Naval Forces in Europe, 1940-46, 1947, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 23, Box 24)
    - ComNavEu monograph, United States-British Naval Relations 1939-1942, 1947, undated, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - Ghormley mission (Box 24)
      - Interview with Austin, 1966 (Box 24)
      - Memoranda and notes, 1940-1941 (Box 24)
      - Miscellaneous, 1940-1941, undated (Box 24)
    - U.S.-British Naval Cooperation 1940-45, undated, (3 folders) (Box 24)
- Classified, 1955-1967 (Box CL 1)
  Documents containing national security information removed from the collection.
  Arranged and described according to the series and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Correspondence (Box CL 1)
    - General (Box CL 1)
      - 1955, Jan.-June (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
      - 1955, July-Aug. (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
      - 1955, Sept.-Dec. (Container 4) (Box CL 1)
      - 1958, Apr.-May (Container 5) (Box CL 1)
      - 1958, June-July (Container 5) (Box Cl 1)
      - 1958, Oct.-Dec. (Container 5) (Box CL 1)
      - 1959, Jan.-May (Container 5) (Box CL 1)
      - 1965, Mar.-Aug. (Container 10) (Box CL 1)
      - 1965, Sept.-Dec. (Container 10) (Box CL 1)
      - 1966, Jan.-Apr. (Container 10) (Box CL 1)
      - 1966, Aug.-Dec. (Container 10) (Box CL 1)
      - 1967, Jan.-May (Container 10) (Box CL 1)
      - 1967, June-Dec. (Container 11) (Box CL 1)
  - Speeches and Writings (Box CL 1)
    - Speeches (Box CL 1)
      - By Austin, 1966 (Container 14) (Box CL 1)
  - Subject File (Box CL 1)
    - Submarines (Box CL 1)
      - Thresher, summary of events, 1963 (Container 23) (Box CL 1)
- Top Secret, 1955 (Box TS 1)
  - Correspondence (Box TS 1)
    - General, 1955, Jan.-June, undated (Container 4) (Box TS 1)
- North American Treaty Organization, 1955-1959 (Box NATO 1)
  - Correspondence (Box NATO 1)
    - General (Box NATO 1)
      - 1955, Sept.-Dec. (Container 4) (Box NATO 1)
      - 1958, Apr.-May (Container 5) (Box NATO 1)
      - 1958, Oct.-Dec. (Container 5) (Box NATO 1)
      - 1959, Jan.-May (Container 5) (Box NATO 1)